Hey everybody, welcome
to the content video
going over section 3.11 of your textbook.
It says program development Sentinel
controlled repetition, but really
we're just going to call them
Sentinel values. And there's something
that you use in line with while loops
to control the flow of the loop.
So normally when the risk that
we run with using a while loop as
opposed to a for loop is that a
while loop can often spin up into
an infinite loop. And so there's
a couple of different ways we
can stop an infinite loop from
occurring using a break or continue
ensuring the condition becomes
false at some point and one of
those methods is called a sentinel
value and it's called a sentinel
because a sentinel is something
that kind of watches for
something else and so a sentinel
value is just something that's going
to watch for a certain thing to
appear in our code so let's go
ahead and jump over into our code
space and i'll show you what i
I mean, I did not spell that
right, sentinel values. Okay, so
let's say that we have a
variable. Let's call it selection.
And let's just set that
equal to zero for now.
And then we're going to set
up our while loop. So I'm
going to say while selection
is not equal to five.
We'll do something like this.
will say print welcome to the
happy message program we'll
print out another line that says
enter one of the following options
we'll call them selections.
One, I don't know how
to show the weather.
And selection two is how
is my day going to go?
That's another option and then
we'll see this at the end we'll say
something like select five to
quit something like that and then
we'll we'll do an if statement
in here we'll say if selection is
equal to one we'll print out whoops
we accidentally ran that. Brent,
the weather is great.
And then elif, selection is two.
Brent,
your day will be amazing.
And then
five, we will say thanks for
using the happy message program.
And we'll see what happens.
All right, let's run this.
Oh dear. Oh, we forgot to get input
from the user, so that's problem um
hang on so selection is going to
equal int input enter your selection
and then we won't just
run our loop forever okay
so how here's our happy message
program enter one of the following
show the weather how's my day going
to go or five to quit so let's
see how our day is going to go one
all right so uh let's see did it
print it out oh the weather is great
perfect so let's hit two your day
will be amazing one again two again
one one etc etc this will continue
looping until we hit five thanks
for using the happy message
program so the sentinel value is
watching for that selection to become
the value it's looking for so
it knows to quit the program
so that's kind of all i wanted
to talk about with Sentinels.
And that concludes this content
video. Thanks for watching.